Every man dies, not every man really lives.
Braveheart is a action, drama, history film directed by Mel Gibson.
Enraged at the slaughter of Murron, his new bride and childhood love, Scottish warrior
William Wallace slays a platoon of the local English lord's soldiers.
This leads the village to revolt and, eventually, the
entire country to rise up against English rule.
William Wallace, played by Mel Gibson.
Murron MacClannough, played by Catherine McCormack.
Princess Isabelle, played by Sophie Marceau.
King Edward, played by Patrick McGoohan.
Robert the Bruce, played by Angus Macfadyen.
Hamish Campbell, played by Brendan Gleeson.
Braveheart is a 1995 American epic historical war drama film directed and produced by Mel Gibson, who portrays Scottish
warrior Sir William Wallace in the First War of Scottish Independence against King Edward I of England.
The film also stars Sophie Marceau, Patrick McGoohan,
Catherine McCormack and Angus Macfadyen.
The story is inspired by Blind Harry's 15th century epic poem The Actes and Deidis of the Illustre and
Vallyeant Campioun Schir William Wallace and was adapted for the screen by Randall Wallace.
Development on the film initially started at
Metro-Goldwyn-Mayer (MGM) when producer Alan Ladd Jr.
picked up the project from Wallace, but when MGM was going through new
management, Ladd left the studio and took the project with him.
Despite initially declining, Gibson eventually decided to
direct the film and to star as Wallace.
The film, which was produced by Gibson's Icon Productions and The Ladd Company, was distributed by
Paramount Pictures in the United States and Canada and by 20th Century Fox in other countries.
Released on May 24, 1995, Braveheart was a critical and commercial success, receiving praise for its battle scenes, production
design, musical score, and acting performances, though it received some criticism for its historical inaccuracies.
The film also garnered numerous awards including
the Academy Award for Best Picture.
A legacy sequel, Robert the Bruce, was released in 2019.
The film explores themes of england, scotland, loss of
loved one, idealism, based on true story.
The tone is emotional.